When you have a read-based path traversal,
it's easy game. You just read a file usually
at /etc/passwd and you get a quick payout. But
what about file write? You have to somehow prove
the vulnerability exists. Usually you don't
know where are you at and you have to watch
out to not overwrite a sensitive file because you
may disrupt the service. To answer this question,
I studied all the path traversal reports that I
found in the internet and I saw which one of them
were write-based path traversals and if yes, what
file did the hunters write. In this video I will
show you those results along with some methods to
escalate path traversal to an RCE. Enjoy! If it's
your first time here, I do these case studies
regularly. I take a bug class, I extract all
the reports that I can find in the internet and
then I study those reports. I already did SSRFs,
XSSs, IDORs and SQL injections and path traversals
are the fifth vulnerability class. They are mostly
available in BBRE Premium but they always share
some part to the public for free, such as in this
case I share the part where I will show you which
file did the hunters write to prove the impact.
So in most cases actually hunters didn't
really write any specific files. In these
cases the hunters would just write a
file that's outside the directory so
they would prove that they can write a file
where they shouldn't, outside the safe directory,
but they wouldn't really care about
what the file content or file name.
Like in this case we have a write based path
traversal in croquis vulnerability in GitLab
and we can see here that the hunter
would just write a temporary file,
a test file write txt because if you write a
file outside the safe directory obviously it's
not the directory where the file should have been
saved. This is enough to prove to the program,
especially to a mature program like GitLab, that
you can really write a file anywhere and often
you can turn it into an RCE. In some programs
you also have to prove this. In this case,
in case of GitLab, I think they just believe
that if you can have a file right you can easily
just turn it into an RCE. And this is the
trend here that these reports with writing
any file but writing it outside safe directory
is present in applications where hunters have
access to the source code. It's open source
and hunters just install this on their own
machine where they can monitor what files are
being created and it just makes it easier to
detect a path traversal like this because if
it's a black box test you may just struggle
to do anything. Also in this case study I noticed
much more than usual zero days like bugs in Ruby
on Rails, bugs in Apache, bugs in Node.js. There
were many many more of them compared to other case
studies that I have done. While the overall amount
of reports, the number of reports was smaller. It
was only 74 reports of path traversals that I
found online which is way less than for example
XSS. And some bugs were like this. We can see it's
a bug in the library in Ruby and the hunter just
creates their own vulnerable source code. It's not
even a direct attack on the web application right
in Ruby or created in Ruby but it's just a library
bug and in this case also it's just creating a
temporary file in arbitrary directory and the
hunter didn't have to prove anything more.
Here we also have a very interesting bug. A bug
that I was not aware of because I'm not a mobile
hacker but the report is partially disclosed but
it's really describing what happened there. So we
have a typical zip slip attack where the attacker
can create a malicious zip with a file that's
outside the safe directory after unpacking the
archive. Two weeks ago I created a video about
my codeQL query to detect these kinds of bugs
so watch the video if you haven't already. But
what happens here is this is not an attack on
the server. This is an attack on the mobile app
and the way it works is for some reason,
I'm not sure for what reason, the file
is extracted on the mobile phone of the victim
and there within the file system of the mobile
the file is extracted outside the safe
directory. In this case the hunter has shown
that just overwriting apps private folders.
I'm not sure what's the real impact of this
but there was another very similar report in slack
where the hunter was able to somehow, it was not
disclosed exactly how, was able to leak access
tokens of the victim using this very attack.
Going forward in three cases the hunters were
able to upload just a shell to the server which
is I think the most straightforward way
to exploit a write-based path traversal.
It will not work in modern programming
languages like Python, like Node.js.
It will work in PHP based technologies. Here we
have a bug in Apache so this is more general.
I believe the hunter simply used PHP as an
example because why not because they could
and in this case you can just upload your shell
anywhere. This report is very interesting because
take a look at this bypass. I'm not sure if
you recognize this but the encoded %32 means
digit two and %65 means letter f, small f. If you
decode these and join it with this % sign you get
%2f which is regular encoded forward slash but
what we see here is we have an unencoded % in
the beginning and then we have the 2f encoded so
this is not a typical double URL encoding payload
because what should happen here is I believe
according to the specs this should be
invalid input. This should be denied because
the percent sign is not followed by a hex number
and this is probably what happened is
the first component would see this,
would ignore this case that I just told you
about, would decode these two characters to 2f
and then the next component, the next component
may be just a function or whatever happens there,
I didn't study it in detail, takes the %2f
which is a regular encoded forward slash
and decodes it leading to this pass traversal
and this is a very good example of why sometimes
we should look for inconsistencies and when you
have an inconsistency it is enough to have a bug
because there is nothing inherently bad about
accepting this invalid input if your component
is on its own but in this case with many
transformations happening to the URL it led
to a bug, it led to a critical pass traversal in
Apache which is something but we also have more
payloads that probably they don't
look like valid URL encoded strings.
So it was an interesting one, we also had
one bug in WordPress where the hunter also
I think only mentioned that it can
lead to an RCE, he didn't actually
exploit it I believe and this is something you
can exploit in WordPress or in PHP based app but
if you're working with Python with Ruby this
will not work because Python or Ruby do not
process files the same way PHP does. In PHP you
can just upload the file to a particular directory
and then you can just send a URL, send a
request and if the file is in the directory
it will be returned. Most modern languages
don't work this way and you can't do this
so as simply as you can in PHP but you can still
get something similar. Here we have an example of
another zero day in Ruby on Rails and in this
case the hunter was able to, it was obviously
also file based, file write based vulnerability
and to exploit this vulnerability the hunter
would overwrite a template. So the way Ruby
on Rails application works is you have some
templates that are usually ERB templates which
means it's saved in a file called text.erb in
this case I believe it's often html.erb and it
looks like a normal html but inside you can have
variables like this so you can have a dynamic
html and contrary to normal shell uploads which
won't work in Ruby this can work in Ruby so
when the hunter would overwrite this file
it may look like a very random name but if you
are familiar with Ruby you probably can predict
that this path would exist and the hunter would
just overwrite with this bug this file with an
arbitrary command because the template allows the
user to execute arbitrary Ruby code which also in
this case means executing system level commands
so it is a proper RCE and then when you upload
something like this it means that the controller
of books which is supposed to show you a book
will try to open this file and fill it with some
information about the book so to trigger the RCE
you have to send another request which will speak
to the books controller in this case and it will
just fetch any book and in this case it will try
to it will try to execute this template which also
executes this code and the hunter proved it by
just using the ls command and the file is here we
had touch me which means it creates an empty file
called me and it was created another case where
the hunter just had access to the source code
and had everything under control with blackbox
test it is perfectly possible to predict this path
but it's definitely harder than doing it whitebox
so watch out for this and also if you have a file
write based path traversal or another bug when you
can write files and you're not working with php
try to see if the application works with template
files because overwriting a template file may
be the easiest way to turn your bug into an RCE
and finally there was also one bug where the
RCE exploit was done by overwriting the ssh
authorized keys so the way it works is you have
a file in linux that's ssh.ssh authorized keys
which contains public encryption keys and when
you log into the server you can use your username
and password if that's enabled but if you are
authenticating yourself with your private key
and your public key is in the authorized keys
file it means you can log in automatically to
the server and this is what the hunter did here
he overwrote the ssh authorized keys file with the
content of his public ssh key which meant that
when now authenticating to the target machine
he could authenticate with his private key which
is easy. The problem with this works magnificently
if you have access to the attack machine the
network access over port 2020 which is which
should be rare and also the machine has to be
configured to not prevent this attack then then
it works like a charm in this case we have we have
gitlab so the hunter could set it up as he wanted
in case of a black box test it shouldn't work
it may work so you should always try this but
it should not work because the machine should
not expose port 2020 to the internet without a
vpn or or whatever but in case you need this
in case you are in the internal assessment
definitely you can exploit file right by
overwriting authorized keys with your public
key and then you just ssh into the machine and
you have a shell and these are all the different
files that were wrote which I saw during this
case study I hope that you did learn some new
tricks in this video if you did leave a like and
if you enjoyed this small part of the case study
if you join BBRE premium you will get access to
the whole case study as well as the previous case
studies about ssrfs xss idors and sql injections
and if you want to watch another video with the
free part of the case study I suggest you this
one where I broke down what payloads for xss
were hunter using to get the biggest payouts
for now thank you for watching and goodbye!